CURRICULUM VITAE

Nilmini Thilakarathna

Senior Lecturer / Chartered Quantity Surveyor BSc.(QS)Hons, MSc.(Proj. Mngt), MPhil F.I.Q.S.SL, MNZIQS 2C, Rennie Street, Green Island, Dunedin, New Zealand +64212071204, Nilmini. Thilakarathna@op.ac.nz



Personality

A competent lecturer with more than 7 years' experience as a senior lecturer / course coordinator in Level 5 to 8 Qualifications in Quantity Surveying & Project Management including Diplomas, Degrees and Masters and research supervisions.

A well trained Quantity Surveyor with more than 20 years' experience in rendering cost consultancy service based on the standards, for Clients to secure their interests in construction projects from inception to completion through proper accountability and cost auditing in buildings and infrastructure development projects in Sri Lanka.

Key capabilities are teamwork, work balanced life, Effective communication, manage resources effectively, accepting challenges, Negotiation, Analytical skill, Data Presenting, Decision making, Self-Motivation, Adopting quickly to a new environment

Qualifications

Professional Qualification	Chartered Quantity Surveyor – Fellow Member of Institute of Quantity Surveyors in Sri Lanka
	Member of New Zealand Institute of Quantity Surveyor

Academic Qualifications

- ✓ Following a **PhD in "Psychology in Lean Construction"** since 2018 at AUT University, Auckland, New Zealand
- ✓ Master of Philosophy (MPhil) 2015, University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka
- ✓ **Master of Project Management (MSc)** 2011, University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka
- ✓ **Bachelor of Science** in Quantity Surveying (BSc. QS. Hons.) 1995, University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

Other Qualifications (in New Zealand)

- ✓ Following GDTE (Graduate Diploma in Tertiary Education), Otago Polytechnic
- ✓ IELTS English test overall 6.5 with 8 for speaking in 2018
- ✓ Successfully completed "Introduction to Tiriti Waitangi" NZQA US 7926 in 2018
- ✓ Successfully completed NZIQS Code of Conduct Test in 2019

Publications

- a. Transfer of construction project Knowledge through Lesson Learned Practices at **PAQS Conference 2011**, Sri Lanka based on the MSc Research on
- b. Preliminary Literature Review into Lean Construction Implementation based on the MPhil Research at CIOB World Construction Symposium **2012**, Sri Lanka
- c. *Lean Construction Implementation* based on the MPhil at FARU symposium **2012**, Sri Lanka
- **d.** Significance of minimizing Non-Value Adding activities using Lean Techniques based on the MPhil Research on Lean Construction at CIB MENA **2014**, Saudi Arabia
- e. A tool for assessing the Lean Maturity in Construction Projects based on the MPhil Research at CIOB World Construction Symposium **2018**, Sri Lanka
- f. Lean Implementation framework, SIT /OP research symposium, March 2018, SIT, Invercargill
- g. Psychology in lean construction: A framework for improving the flow process in Construction activities,
 PAQS 2019 (Abstract Accepted and Paper is in progress)

Working Experience

October 2017 to date

Senior Lecturer

College of Engineering, Construction and Living Science Otago Polytechnic (Dunedin)

Developing course materials and lecturing, supervising to the undergraduates

Expected outcomes;

Prepare thoroughly own course plans, outlines and materials for delivery of assigned classes

Facilitate learning by different approaches which may include, presenting lectures, tutorials, seminars, workshops and papers

Apply effective communication skills in diverse learning situations.

Teaching for 2018: Cost Planning, Procurement & Tendering, Estimating

Teaching for 2019: Procurement & tendering, Property Investment, Contract Administration,

Property Development and Research Project.

March 2016 to September 2017:

Free-lance Practitioner in Construction Cost Auditing

Auditing the process including reviewing Financial Feasibility reports, Contract Documents, Final Accounts for cost savings and future improvements by documenting lesson-learned practices in order to minimize non-value adding activities in construction processes.

Senior Visiting Lecturer

- 1. KDU, QS Department for Intake 32 & 33 from 2016 to date
- 2. BCAS, QS Department for, BSc QS Degree from 2010 to date
- 3. BCAS, QS Department for RICS, UOW, MSc QS Degree from 2017 to date
- 4. BCAS, QS Department for, HND Edexcel from 2010 to date
- 5. IQSSL, professional Level III from 2016

Curriculum Development

- 1. BSc (QS) Program, Open University of Sri Lanka
- 2. BSc (QS) Program, SAITM University, Malambe

Oct' 2013 to March 2016:

Group Chief Quantity Surveyor

Prime Residencies (Pvt) Ltd, Colombo

A leading Property developer in Sri Lanka for been in the business for the last 20 years providing solutions for lands, houses & apartments

Advice the Top Management for new projects by preparing Project Feasibility Reports, Business development plans, Strategic changes, cost controlling aspects focusing on the proper balance of cash Inflow and cash outflow of the company.

Control the Cost with required documentation in approvals from different regulatory bodies according to Condominium Regulations, setting up and maintaining Management Corporations

Managing the Department of Quantity Surveying for Pre-contract & Post Contract Activities as Client / Consultant to the 15-20 Building Projects (Annual Work Done US\$ 40,000,000) with problem-solving and decision making in contract administration on Lump Sum Fixed-priced contracts.

<u>January 2009 to Oct'2013</u>:

Cost Consultant on Free Lance Practice

QS Consultant - Square Mech Engineering, a leading contracting organization with the specialization in Buildings, Water Supply and Roads including re-setting up QS department with new strategies to be a competitive bidder in tendering, Evaluating claims, Disputes, variations, final accounts of on-going projects

Cost Consultant - SMR Engineering, a leading steel building contractor, Factory Building for Ware House Logistics (Pvt) Ltd., Welgama, Malwana

Consultant Quantity Surveyor - QServe (Pvt) Ltd, Albert Place, Dehiwala including estimation, securitizing interim / Final payments and curriculum development for QS Education

An external Estimator - NDB Bank, Home Loan Division, Colombo 03 in Preparation of Bill of Quantities

Senior Lecturer

Resource Person - Department of Building Economics, the University of Moratuwa for lecturing, Industrial training placement and assessments for the Degree Programs of Quantity Surveying & Facilities management

Senior Lecturer & Internal Verifier - British College of Applied Studies, a leading QS Campus for contract management, Tender estimation & Construction contract law modules in the programs in Sri Lanka, Qatar & Oman affiliated with Edexcel, University of Wolver Hampton, University of London South Bank (UK)

Program Coordinator & Senior Lecturer - British College of Applied Studies, affiliated University of Wolver Hampton (UK) for BSc Degree in Quantity Surveying

April 2003 to Jan'2009:

Senior Quantity Surveyor

Ceylinco Housing & Real Estate Co. Ltd.

A leading Real Estate Company for detached housing schemes in Colombo & Suburbs: Establish the Quantity Surveying Division with basic standard requirements and manage QS activities in Client perspective, including Feasibility Studies, Cash flow management, Evaluating selling prices, Tendering, Pricing, Budgeting, Cost Controlling, Contract Administration with Variations & Claims Dispute Resolution, Final Accounts based on employer designed terms and conditions. Approximate Turn over per year US\$ 800,000)

Jan' 1996 to March 2002: Quantity Surveyor

Finco Limited, Engineering Directorate, Sri Lanka

A leading specialized supplier and subcontractor on waterproofing

Worked as a Quantity Surveyor/member of the Senior Management in the following areas

- Preparation of Competitive Bids
- Evaluation of Interim & Final Bills
- Preparation of Pre contract documents
- Procurement systems for the Material requirement
- Costing the imported construction chemicals
- Technical Consultation for customers in specialized areas such as waterproofing, crack repairs & joint sealants

Special Achievements

- Delivering Lecturers in Qatar and Oman attached to British College of Applied Studies for the Degree Programs awarded by University of Wolverhampton, University of London South Bank 2010 to 2016
- Overseas training at Singapore for Waterproofing and construction chemicals in 1996

Other Social Involvements

- Treasurer of Women In Construction, Sri Lanka (WICK) in 2016
- Past President of QS Alumni Association, University of Moratuwa year 2009/2010
- Member of Professional affairs Board (PAB) of Institute of Quantity Surveyors in Sri Lanka since 2016
- Member of Board of Memberships Institute of Quantity Surveyors in Sri Lanka since 2011
- Executive member of QS Alumni Association, University of Moratuwa year 2010 to 2013
- Asst. Secretary of Past Pupils Association of Anuradhapura Central College, Colombo Branch from 2009 to 2011
- Executive Council Member of Past Pupils Association of Anuradhapura Central College Colombo Branch 2007/2008

Personal Information

Date of birth : 1st July 1969

Age : 49 years

Sex : Female